<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC
  "-//Apache Software Foundation//DTD XDOC 1.0//EN"
  "http://maven.apache.org/dtd/xdoc_1_0.dtd">

<document>
  <properties>
    <title>How to encrypt user passwords</title>
    <author email="dfernandez AT users.sourceforge.net">
      Daniel Fernandez Garrido
    </author>
  </properties>
  <body>
  
    <section name="How to encrypt user passwords">

      <div align="right">
        <i>
          by Daniel Fernandez Garrido &lt;dfernandez AT
          users.sourceforge.net>
        </i>
      </div>

      <subsection name="1. Overview">

        <p>
          Almost all modern web applications need, in one way or
          another, to encrypt their users' passwords. We could say that,
          from the moment that an application has users, and users
          sign in using a password, these passwords have to be stored in
          an encrypted way.
        </p>
        <p>
          There are some intuitive reasons for this: our data
          stores can be compromised, and so can our communications.
          But the most important reason is that <b>we have to think of our
          users' passwords as sensitive personal data</b>. Their passwords
          are their key to their privacy, so they are personal, they are
          sensitive, and no one (not even us) has the right to know
          them. And we must honor this if we want to gain our user's
          trust.
        </p>

      </subsection>

      <subsection name="2. The algorithm">

        <p>
          So, we have to encrypt passwords, but... how? Here comes our
          first rule:
        </p>

        <div
          style="border: 1px dotted #000; background-color: #f5e1b6; padding: 20px 40px 20px 40px; margin-left: 40px; margin-right: 40px; font-weight: bold;">
          I. Encrypt passwords using one-way techniques,
          this is, digests.
        </div>

        <p>
          This is because, except for some specific scenarios (mainly
          regarding legacy integration), <i>there is absolutely no reason
          for a password being decrypted</i>. If you encrypt your passwords
          using password-based encryption (a two-way technique) and an attacker gets to know
          your encryption password, all of your user passwords will be revealed
          (and, probably, all at a time). If you don't have such
          encryption password (or key) to be able to decrypt, this risk disappears,
          and the attacker will have to trust on brute force or similar
          strategies.
        </p>

        <p>
          <b>'But what if my one of my users loses his/her password? Can't I
          remind it to him/her?' The answer is a loud and clear NO.</b> Not only you cannot
          perform such thing as reminding their passwords to them, but
          in fact you should not even have a way to get to read/know/see
          your users' passwords, no matter if you are the system
          administrator! <i>If one of your users lose his/her password, just reset
          it to a new value and send him/her a message to their verified
          email address with the new one, asking to change it
          as soon as possible</i>.
        </p>

        <p>
          Now that it is clear that password digesting is a must, which
          digest algorithm should we use? Well, there are several, and it largely
          depends on your needs. The most used ones are:
        </p>

        <ul>
          <li>
            <p>MD5 algorithm</p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p>
              SHA family: SHA-1 algorithm and SHA-2 variants (SHA-224,
              SHA-256, SHA-384 and SHA-512)
            </p>
          </li>
        </ul>

        <p>
          In most cases, <b>both MD5 or SHA-1 will be adequate choices for
          password digesting</b>, although applying these algorithms will
          not be enough, as we will see later on.
        </p>

        <p>
          When we are told that we should use digests for password
          encryption, and given that digests are one-way techniques, the
          next question that arises to our minds usually is: <b>'If I cannot 
          decrypt passwords... how will I check if my
          users entered the right one?'</b>
        </p>

        <p>
          There is a very simple answer to this question, which we will adopt as
          our second rule:
        </p>

        <div
          style="border: 1px dotted #000; background-color: #f5e1b6; padding: 20px 40px 20px 40px; margin-left: 40px; margin-right: 40px; font-weight: bold;">
          II. Match input and stored passwords by comparing digests, not
          unencrypted strings.
        </div>

        <p>
          Which means that, once our users have entered their passwords
          at sign in, we will digest their input with the same algorithm
          we have previously used when storing the password, and then compare both
          digests. As digest algorithms guarantee that two equal inputs
          will get equal digests (which is not true in the opposite
          direction), if digests match we can then consider the password 
          input by the user as valid.
        </p>

      </subsection>

      <subsection name="3. Improving the security of our digests">

        <p>
          All the digest algorithms (also <i>cryptographic hash
          functions</i>) mentioned above share a feature: they are public. They are
          well-known and largely implemented algorithms, and so anyone
          can use them, and not only us.
        </p>

        <p>
          If anyone can use the same algorithm that we use, and for some
          reason attackers get to see our database of password digests, how
          can we be sure that they will not be able to guess some of our
          user passwords by simply trying all the possibilities until they find
          one which digest matches the stored one (brute force)?
        </p>

        <p>
          Well, the answer is... we cannot. But we can make this such an
          overwhelming and time-consuming task that they will not want to,
          unless they can wait for eternity.
          For achieving this, two concepts come in our help: the <b>salt</b>
          and the <b>iteration count</b>.
        </p>


        <h4>3.1. The salt</h4>

        <p>
          The salt is a sequence of bytes that is added to the password
          before being digested. This makes our digests different to
          what they would be if we encrypted the password alone, and as
          a result protects us against dictionary attacks. We can adopt
          two different strategies regarding salt:
        </p>

        <ul>
          <li>
            <p>
              Use a <b>fixed salt</b>, a sequence of bytes that we will use for
              digesting every password. We can keep this salt hidden and
              consider it an added security value, but it can make our
              system more vulnerable to birthday attacks and, in
              general, attacks driven against our database of passwords
              as a whole.
            </p>
          </li>
        </ul>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <p>
              Use a <b>variable salt</b>, which is usually a safer option
              (specially if it is random). This is generated or computed
              separately for each password being digested and it allows
              each stored password to be decoupled from the others,
              creating a stronger overall protection and highly
              improving safety for attacks driven against our database
              of passwords as a whole.
            </p>
          </li>
        </ul>

        <p>
          In practice, random (or at least variable) salt is a much
          better idea because, although <b>its being random will force us
          to store it unencrypted along with the digest (so that we can
          recover it)</b> and this will make it trivial for an attacker to
          know it, it will still let each of our users' passwords remain
          decoupled from the rest, so that they will have to be attacked
          separately.
        </p>

        <p>
          Think that, if we use a fixed salt and the attacker gets to
          know this fixed salt, the security of the whole database of
          passwords will be dramatically decreased. And there are
          several ways an attacker can get to know this salt, like
          applying brute force on his own password or on a password
          he/she has got somehow from a valid user. <b>In a fixed-salt scenario, a
          weak user could lead us to a weak overall password system</b>.
        </p>

        <p>
          Nevertheless, if still you want to keep some part of the salt 
          secret, a good approach could be a mix of both techniques,
          using a salt composed of both a fixed secret portion and a
          random one, with only the random bytes being stored undigested
          along with the digest result.
        </p>


        <p>
          The minimum recommended size of salt is 8 bytes. If a mixed
          approach is used, at least 8 of its bytes should be random.
          This said, we can state our third rule:
        </p>


        <div
          style="border: 1px dotted #000; background-color: #f5e1b6; padding: 20px 40px 20px 40px; margin-left: 40px; margin-right: 40px; font-weight: bold;">
          III. Use a salt containing at least 8 random bytes, and attach
          these random bytes, undigested, to the result.
        </div>



        <h4>3.2. The iteration count</h4>

        <p>
          The iteration count refers to the number of times that the
          hash function with which we are digesting is applied to its
          own results.
        </p>

        <p>
          This means that, once we have selected a salt and concatenated
          the password to it, <b>we will have to apply the hash function
          (say, an MD5 algorithm), get the result, and then pass it
          again as input to the same hash function</b>, then do the same
          again and again and again... a number of times.
        </p>

        <p>
          The minimum recommended number of iterations is 1,000, and it
          will provide us with a good amount of extra security. Think
          that, when you are creating a single password digest for a new
          user, the difference between applying the hash function once
          or a thousand times won't be a problem for you, maybe a couple
          hundreds of milliseconds... but attackers would have to
          generate an enormous amount of tentative password digests when
          brute-forcing and, <b>for an attacker, the difference between
          applying the hash function once and applying it a thousand
          times for each try would be a real computational problem</b>.
        </p>

        <p>So, it seems that we have a fourth rule:</p>

        <div
          style="border: 1px dotted #000; background-color: #f5e1b6; padding: 20px 40px 20px 40px; margin-left: 40px; margin-right: 40px; font-weight: bold;">
          IV. Iterate the hash function at least 1,000 times.
        </div>


        <h4>3.3. Put graphically</h4>
        
        <p>
        We can represent this whole process of using a salt and an iteration count
        graphically as this:
        </p>

        <div align="center">
          <img src="images/passwordEncryption.png" alt="Password encryption process"/>
        </div>
        

      </subsection>

      <subsection
        name="4. Character string to byte sequence translation">
        
        <p>
          Before being able of correctly storing our password digests, 
          there still is
          something that we should care about, which is the mismatch between
          character strings and byte sequences: <b>two identical character
          strings may be represented with different byte sequences depending
          on the encoding being applied for translation (ISO-8859-1, UTF-8, etc...)</b>.
        </p>
          
        <p>
          This will affect us because passwords
          are usually input by users as character strings, but digest
          algorithms work at a byte level.
        </p>
        

       <h4>4.1. Troubleshooting encoding at password input</h4>

        <p>
          Imagine that a new user signs up with a password
          containing a non-ASCII character, and your sign-up
          application, running on a Windows 2000 machine in Western
          Europe, converts the input character string to bytes without
          choosing a specific encoding for the operation, and thus
          using the default one, which in that Windows system would be
          ISO-8859-1. The sign-up logic digests the resulting bytes and
          the password gets stored.
        </p>

        <p>
          Then, this user comes around again and this time he/she does
          not visit your sign-up application, but instead some other app
          running on the same password database but on a Linux machine.
          The user correctly inputs his/her password and... they don't
          match!
        </p>

        <p>
          Why? because most Linux systems use UTF-8 as a default
          encoding, and thus the passwords input by the user in the two
          different scenarios have been translated into different byte
          sequences by each of the machines, affecting correct password
          matching.
        </p>

        <p>
          How to solve this: by setting a fixed encoding for
          string-to-byte translations. Here comes rule number five:
        </p>

        <div
          style="border: 1px dotted #000; background-color: #f5e1b6; padding: 20px 40px 20px 40px; margin-left: 40px; margin-right: 40px; font-weight: bold;">
          V. Prior to digesting, perform string-to-byte sequence
          translation using a fixed encoding, preferably UTF-8.
        </div>

        <p>
          If you are using Java, where String objects are encoding-independent
          (although backed by UTF-16), you won't have to worry whether your application
          uses ISO-8859-1 or any other encoding instead of UTF-8 for its user 
          interface, as will not be necessary that the encoding for password digesting matches
          that of the user interface. It is just necessary that this
          encoding be a fixed one, and UTF-8 will bring you the right
          balance between size and charset completeness (Unicode).
        </p>


       <h4>4.2. Troubleshooting encoding at digest storage</h4>

        <p>
          We will normally want to manage and store the
          digested password as a character string, but
          the digest function will output a sequence of bytes
          which will not necessarily represent a valid character string
          in any encoding. So, translating our digested byte sequence
          back into a character string could not be possible, and we
          could risk data loss when doing it.
        </p>

        <p>
          This is where BASE64 encoding comes to the rescue. <b>By encoding
          our digested sequence of bytes in BASE64, we will make sure
          that the output byte sequence represents a valid,
          displayable, US-ASCII character string</b>. So we will be
          able to safely translate the BASE64-encoded byte sequence into
          a character string specifying US-ASCII as the encoding.
        </p>

        <div
          style="border: 1px dotted #000; background-color: #f5e1b6; padding: 20px 40px 20px 40px; margin-left: 40px; margin-right: 40px; font-weight: bold;">
          VI. Finally, apply BASE64 encoding and store the digest as an
          US-ASCII character string.
        </div>
      
      </subsection>

      <subsection
        name="5. Summary of rules for encrypting user passwords">

        <p>
        We now have a complete list of rules to be applied:
        </p>

        <div
          style="border: 1px dotted #000; background-color: #f5e1b6; padding: 20px 40px 20px 40px; margin-left: 40px; margin-right: 40px; font-weight: bold;">
          <p>
            I. Encrypt passwords using one-way techniques,
            this is, digests.
          </p>
          <p>
            II. Match input and stored passwords by comparing digests, not
            unencrypted strings.
          </p>
          <p>
            III. Use a salt containing at least 8 random bytes, and
            attach these random bytes, undigested, to the result.
          </p>
          <p>IV. Iterate the hash function at least 1,000 times.</p>
          <p>
            V. Prior to digesting, perform string-to-byte sequence
            translation using a fixed encoding, preferably UTF-8.
          </p>
          <p>
            VI. Finally, apply BASE64 encoding and store the digest as
            an US-ASCII character string.
          </p>
        </div>

      </subsection>

      <subsection name="6. Doing it in Java">

        <p>
        <b>The easiest way of encrypting passwords in Java using the explained
        techniques is <a href="encrypting-passwords.html">using Jasypt</a></b>,
        which already does all this processing transparently for you.
        </p>
        <p>
        If we cannot use jasypt, or if for some reason we wish to develop encryption 
        features ourselves, we will need the following tools for our task:
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li><p><b><tt>java.security.MessageDigest</tt></b> for creating
              digests. This class allows to specify the digest algorithm
              we wish to use.</p></li>
          <li><p><b><tt>java.security.SecureRandom</tt></b> for generating
              random salt in a secure manner, using algorithms like
              SHA1PRNG.</p></li>
          <li><p>The <b><tt>java.lang.String.getBytes(String charsetName)</tt></b>
              method, for obtaining a byte sequence from the input String,
              specifying a fixed encoding (<tt>"UTF-8"</tt>).</p></li>
          <li><p><b><tt>org.apache.commons.codec.binary.Base64</tt></b>, part
              of the Apache Commons-Codec library, for performing BASE64
              translations on hash output.</p></li>
        </ul>
        
        <p>
        Also, the source code for classes <tt>org.jasypt.digest.StandardByteDigester</tt>
        and <tt>org.jasypt.digest.StandardStringDigester</tt>, available
        at the <a href="source-repository.html">Source Repository</a>, can be used as a guide.
        </p>

      </subsection>

      <subsection name="7. Defense against typical attacks">


        <h4>7.1. Brute force attacks</h4>

        <p><b>Performed on</b>: A single user password.</p>

        <p>
          <b>Description</b>: The attacker tries to get the user's password by
          exhaustively generating all possible passwords, digesting them
          and testing if they match with the user's password digest.
          <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brute_force_attack">Learn more [wikipedia.org]</a>.
        </p>

        <p>
          <b>Our defense</b>: By iterating the hash function to a number like 1,000 (minimum
          recommended), the overhead of password digest creation for the
          user at sign-up or sign-in time is not significant, but the
          accumulated cost for a brute force attacker generating
          millions of digests will be very considerable. Remember that one of
          the best ways to protect your encrypted data is making the cost
          of breaking your security too high to be worth the effort.
        </p>


        <h4>7.2. Dictionary attacks</h4>

        <p>
          <b>Performed on</b>: Either a single user password or a database of user
          passwords as a whole.
        </p>

        <p>
          <b>Description</b>: The attacker tries to get the user's password by
          matching its digest against a set of "most possible" password
          digests, typically generated from a list of words in a
          dictionary. This attack exploits a severe weakness in nowadays
          applications, as an important amount of users set a dictionary
          word as their password. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dictionary_attack">Learn more [wikipedia.org]</a>.
        </p>

        <p>
          <b>Our defense</b>: By adding a random salt, the weakness of the dictionary-based
          passwords many people use is reduced (they no longer are
          dictionary words), and the possibility of the digest appearing
          on a set of digests previously created by the attacker is
          minimal.
        </p>


        <h4>7.3. Birthday attacks</h4>

        <p><b>Performed on</b>: Database of user passwords as a whole.</p>

        <p>
          <b>Description</b>: This attack exploits the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Birthday_paradox">Birthday paradox
          [wikipedia.org]</a>, which in brief states that, having a large
          set of user password digests, the possibilities of generating
          a password which digest collides with at least one of the
          digests in the set is very much higher than what you would
          intuitively expect. And this possibilities increase
          dramatically as the size of the set (the number of users)
          augments. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Birthday_attack">Learn more [wikipedia.org]</a>.
        </p>

        <p>
          <b>Our defense</b>: By adding a random salt the possibilities of a birthday attack
          to succeed are minimum, because the attacker would have to
          attack each password separately, and not the set of passwords
          as a whole, to find a collision. This is because he/she would
          have to find a password that creates the same digest as the
          attacked one using the same salt which was used for digesting
          it, which is different for each password (this is, it would
          become a brute force attack).
        </p>


      </subsection>




    </section>
  </body>
</document>

